"The Role Meat May Play in
Triggering Parkinson's Disease"
Parkinson's disease is an ever-worsening
neurodegenerative disorder that results
in death and affects about 1 in 50
of us when we get older.
A small minority of cases are
genetic and run in families,
but 85 to 90% of cases are sporadic,
meaning they just seemingly pop up
out of nowhere.
It's caused by the death of a certain
kind of nerve cell in the brain.
Once about 70% of them
are gone, the symptoms start.
Okay, so what kills off those cells?
It's still not completely clear,
but the abnormal clumping of a protein
called alpha-synuclein (à-synuclein)
is thought to be involved. Why?
Because if you inject blended
Parkinson's brains into the heads
of rats or monkeys, you can induce
Parkinson's pathology and symptoms,
or even just injecting the pure clumped
à-synuclein strands themselves.
Okay, but how do these clumps
naturally end up in the brain?
It all seems to start in the gut.
The part of the brain where the pathology
often first shows up is directly connected
to the gut, and we have direct
evidence of the spread
of Parkinson's pathology from the
gastrointestinal tract to the brain.
Alpha-synuclein from brains
of Parkinson's patients
is taken up in the gut wall,
and creeping up the vagal nerves
from the gut into the brain.
But this was in rats. If only
we had a way to go back
and look at people's colons
before they got Parkinson's.
And indeed, we can. Old colon
biopsies were dredged up
from people who had later
developed Parkinson's,
and years before symptoms arose, you
could see the à-synuclein in their gut.
Research supported by the Michael J. Fox
Foundation has found
you can reliably distinguish
the colons of patients from controls
by the presence of the Parkinson's
protein lodged in the gut wall.
But how did it get there
in the first place?
Perhaps vertebrate food products
as a potential source
of prion-like à-synuclein.
See, nearly all of the animals
with back bones that we eat--
cows, chickens, pigs, and fish--
express the protein à-synuclein.
And so when we eat common
meat products, when we eat
skeletal muscle, we're
eating nerves, blood cells,
and the muscle cells themselves.
Every pound of meat has up to
like a teaspoon of blood in it
and that alone could be
an à-synuclein source
to potentially trigger
a clumping cascade
of our own à-synuclein in the gut.
Though it may seem intuitive
that dietary à-synuclein could seed
this kind of buildup in our gut,
what evidence do we have
that it's actually happening?
These are pretty interesting data.
There's a surgical procedure
called a vagotomy
in which the big nerve that goes
from your gut to your brain is cut
as an old-timey treatment
for stomach ulcers.
Would cutting communication between the
gut and the brain reduce Parkinson's risk?
Apparently so, suggesting that
the gut to brain vagal nerve
may be critically involved in the
development of Parkinson's disease.
Now, of course, many people regularly
consume meat and dairy products,
but only a small fraction of the general
population will develop Parkinson's.
So there must be other factors at
play that may somehow provide
an opportunity for unwanted
dietary à-synuclein
to enter the host and initiate disease.
For example, your gut becomes leakier
as you age so might that play a role?
Well, what else makes your gut leaky?
Dietary fiber deprivation has also been
shown to degrade the intestinal barrier
and enhance pathogen entry.
So this all raises possibilities
for food-based therapy.
Parkinson's patients have significantly
less Prevotella in their gut, a friendly
fiber-eating flora that bolsters
your intestinal barrier function.
So low levels of Prevotella
are linked to a leaky gut,
which has been linked to
intestinal à-synuclein deposition.
But fiber-rich foods may
bring Prevotella levels back up.
Therefore, by adopting
a plant-based diet,
in addition to getting the beneficial
effects of phytonutrients,
it's possible that increasing
overall fiber intake may modify
the gut microbiome and
gut leakiness in beneficial ways.
So, does a vegan diet, one
with lots of fiber and no meat,
reduce risk for Parkinson's disease?
Parkinson's does appear to
be rare in quasi-vegan cultures.
Rates are about five times lower in rural
sub-Saharan Africa for instance.
Now all this time we were thinking
the benefits seen for Parkinson's
from plant-based diets
was due to the antioxidants
and anti-inflammatory nature
of the animal-free diets,
but maybe it's also due to the increased
intestinal exposure to fiber and
decreased intestinal exposure to
ingested nerves, muscles, and blood.